Ayhan Kaya

LinkedIn | GitHub

P: (518) 226-2555

E: ayhankaya.2061@gmail.com

Adr:Jersey City, NJ 07302 Green Card Holder

DevOps Engineer/Cloud Engineer

Highly adaptable professional DevOps and AWS Certified Cloud engineer who is passionate about the automation of IT processes with 3 + years of experience. I embrace teamwork and also able to work independently. Equipped with remarkable problem solving, multitasking, time management, social and leadership skills. Expert in designing and building effective Continuous Integration and Delivery (CI/CD) pipelines using containerization, orchestration, monitoring, infrastructure automation tools, and configuration management tools with cloud technology solutions.

Technical Skills

- **DevOps Tools:** Kubernetes, Helm Chart, Ansible, Jenkins, Terraform, GitLab, Docker, Docker-Compose, Git, GitLab, GitHub, Maven, Grafana, Prometheus, Slack, Jira, Nexus
- Operating Systems: Microsoft Windows, Linux
- Scripting and Programming Languages: Python, Java, Bash, Unix Shell
- Networking Skills: TCP/IP Suite, DNS, DHCP, LAN, WAN, IPv4, IPv6, Firewall
- Cloud Techonologies:

AWS/EC2, EKS, ECR, VPC, S3, RDS, DynamoDB, Cloudformation, MariaDB, CloudWach, Route53, IAM, Secrets Manager, AWS Lambda, SNS, SQS, Auto-scaling, AWS Load Balancer, Web Application Firewall, Guard Duty, QuickSight, AWS Organizations, AWS API Gateway, Application Migration Service, Aws Cost Management.

Azure / Azure Active Directory, Azure SQL, Vistual Machine, Azure CDN, Azure Fucntion, Azure DevOps

Work Experience

Cloud & DevOps Engineer | NioyaTech LLC, Tysons Corner, Tysons, VA (Remote)

June 2020 - Present

- Developed scripting technologies and coded applications using Python, enabling efficient automation and workflow optimization.
- Used Terraform and Cloudformation to create and manage AWS resources and other services troughout different projects.
- Spearheaded and successfully managed Containerization and Virtualization Projects, leveraging cutting-edge technologies like Docker and Kubernetes to optimize application deployment processes and enhance overall system flexibility.
- Provisined and configured over 20 application deployment using Ansible and Ansible playbooks.
- Established and diligently maintained fully automated CI/CD pipelines for seamless code deployment, leveraging with Jenkins and GitLab, which significantly accelerated software release cycles and ensured enhanced reliability.
- Proficiently monitored, analyzed, and reported performance statistics for cloud-hosted environments using AWS CloudWatch, Prometheus, and Grafana, enabling proactive system management and optimization.
- Successfully built and configured 100+ EC2 instances on the AWS cloud platform, and skillfully managed the configuration of Elastic Load Balancer (ELB) for efficient traffic control among EC2 instances and S3 storage.
- Demonstrated extensive hands-on experience in AWS provisioning and in-depth knowledge of various AWS services.

Graduate Assistant | Operation and Facilities Department, The College of Saint Rose, Albany, NY

Sept 2020 - May 2022

- Oversaw and ensured the smooth operation of the inventory control system, utilizing the TMA application.
- Actively updated and maintained inventory data using the TMA portal, ensuring accuracy and timeliness.
- Prepared and delivered data operation activities, effectively communicating the system's performance to stakeholders.
- Collaborated in the design and preparation of quarterly financial reports and budgeting activities.
- Spearheaded the creation and ongoing maintenance of the departmental database, encompassing data quality review, automated data extraction, and qualitative data collection, alongside developing comprehensive reports.
- Employed SQL to compile and validate data from relational databases, fulfilling business requirements and conducting statistical and geographical analysis to study the distribution and concentration of Key Performance Indicators (KPIs).

Business Intelligence Analyst | TUSAS Engine Industries Inc., Turkey

Aug 2017 - Sept 2019

- Analyzed sales and advisements data to identify significant trends that influenced the company's business strategies.
- Strengthened data analysis capabilities and proficiency in handling large datasets and creating efficient workflows.
- Contributed to a 60% reduction in project timeline by collaborating with cross-functional teams, gathering data requirements, and assisting with data cleaning for Customer Success and Global Analytics teams.

- Conducted regular QA tests on retrieved data, ensuring its accuracy, and saving the Exemption Certificate Management team up to 30% of the time during the data validation process.
- Engaged in diverse professional development programs, encompassing networking, soft skills, data visualization, presentations, time management, and business writing, gaining valuable insights on the influence of soft skills & driving business transformation.

Projects

The Petclinic Microservices Project

- Developed a Dockerized web application using Java Spring Boot and Spring Cloud Frameworks, integrated with a MySQL database.
- Implemented full microservices architecture and established CI/CD pipelines for automated deployment on a Kubernetes cluster with comprehensive monitoring. Managed the Kubernetes cluster efficiently using Rancher.

Web Page Application (PostgreSQL-Nodejs-React) deployed on EC2's with Ansible and Docker

 The Web-Page Application was designed to deploy a web page using Node.js and React Frameworks on the AWS Cloud Infrastructure, facilitated by Ansible.

Microservice Architecture for Phonebook Web Application (Python Flask) with MySQL using Kubernetes

• Created frontend and backend services, both interacting with a dedicated database service and skillfully managed them using Kubernetes deployment.

Dockerization of Bookstore Web API (Python Flask) with MySQL

Developed the Bookstore Web App API for educational purposes, focusing on understanding application dockerization.

Phonebook Application (Python Flask) deployed on AWS environment with Terraform

• Spearheaded the development of a Python Flask-based Phonebook Application, empowering users to effectively manage phonebook records with seamless search, addition, update, and deletion capabilities.

Education

The College of Saint Rose, Albany, NY: Master of Business Administration | GPA: 3.88

May 2022

Marmara University, Turkey: Bachelor of Arts in Economics | GPA: 3.34

June 2017

Certifications and Special Training:

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate | AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner | Sales Skills Boot Camp, The College of Saint Rose
- CCI-Personality Inventory interpretation Training, Master Training International | Personal Data Protection Training
- SAP Basic Training, TUSAS Engine Industries, Inc.

Languages:

English: Full professional proficiency
Turkish: Native or bilingual proficiency
Kurdish: Native or bilingual proficiency